Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translatiors: The Magpie Bridge Brigade
鹊桥小队翻译组
[this episode completed April 2022]
Consort Lumière returns to the palace!
Your Majesties, I have returned.
I wish Your Majesties good health and eternal blessings.
Was everything good on the trip back?
It was.
When His Majesty informed me of your return,
I was overjoyed.
I'm grateful for Your Majesty's care and thoughtfulness.
Since Noble Prince Guo is the ceremonial envoy,
he will announce my conferral on Consort Lumière
to the harem on my behalf.
Now that all the concubines are here,
Yunli, please go ahead.
Yes.
By the grace of Heaven, His Majesty decrees:
"I praise the expanding prosperity of the palace
arising from the gentleness and kindness of the harem."
"Niohuru Zhen Huan, from the prestigious family Niohuru,
is distinguished by her dutifulness and decorum."
"At the Empress Dowager's benevolent behest,
I hereby grant her the title of Consort Lumière."
This is His Majesty’s edict.
Now that Consort Lumière has returned,
I have accomplished my mission.
It must've been an exhausting journey.
I must reward you generously.
If it pleases Your Majesty,
perhaps you could bestow on me some
of the ancient paintings from your collection
so that I can stop longing for them day and night.
All right. Take whichever ones you like.
After Consort Lumière gave birth to
the Fourth Prince years ago,
she put her own well-being behind
and requested to leave the palace to
pray for blessings for our great nation.
I am deeply moved by her sacrifice,
so I promoted her to Consort Lumière
and requested the pleasure of her return.
Rumor has it Consort Lumière
is the previous Concubine Sourire.
Does that matter?
She is ...
whoever His Majesty says she is.
Lumière, I thought I would never be able to see you again.
I'd never imagined this very day.
Years have passed since we last saw each other, Lingrong.
You haven't changed.
Consort Lumière doesn't look wholly well today.
Perhaps because of the exhausting ride.
A pregnant woman shouldn't keep standing here in the wind.
You should return to your palace and rest.
Concubine Vertu has been elated over your return.
To prepare for your return,
His Majesty had the Palace of Eternal Longevity specially restored.
His Majesty thought of everything for your palace, Lumière.
Many antique treasures were retrieved from storage
but we weren't permitted to admire them
until you opened the gates upon your arrival.
Lumière, seeing such magnificence
would truly open our eyes.
You will have plenty of time to visit another day.
It's not necessary to do it now.
Let Consort Lumière settle in first.
I will accompany you to the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
I remember you love to see blooming lotus,
so I had several dozen urns of lotus flowers
moved here to your palace
for you to enjoy at your leisure.
I thank Your Majesty.
When I asked them to refurbish the
Palace of Eternal Longevity,
I ordered them to replicate the "pepper-painted walls."
Just as before, now you still have your pepper-painted room.
No one else who gained favor over these years
has been granted the honor of a pepper-painted room.
I am undeserving of such high favor from Your Majesty.
Come, let us go see your sleeping chamber.
[Virtue renewed daily]
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
The refurbishment of the
Palace of Eternal Longevity was done well.
I'll reward the responsible officers
of the Household Department.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Your Majesty, the Palace of Eternal
Longevity exudes such opulence.
I dare not live here.
Please allow me to live in a different residence.
Huan Huan, you endured so much hardship outside the palace.
What I have done could never
be adequate compensation for your suffering.
Your Majesty must not say that.
Such words sound as if there is distance between us.
You don't need to feel uneasy.
The arrangment was done under my order,
and the Empress thoughtfully made many additional contributions.
Nobody dares to gossip about it.
This incense smells so pleasantly sweet.
Yes, this is the Goose Pear Bedside Incense.
This incense was created by Empress Zhou Ehuang
of the Southern Tang State.
After the demise of the Southern Tang State,
the method of making this incense was long lost.
I wonder how Your Majesty acquired it?
Lingrong is good at crafting incense;
this incense is her handiwork.
She worked hard on this,
mixing hundreds of spices to replicate this ancient incense.
No one else has her attentiveness.
Sometimes my sleep is restless, and
I feel more relaxed when smelling this fragrance.
What a marvelous incense!
It reminds me of the fragrant pear flowers
at the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Those pear trees are excellent,
but they could not be transplanted.
So we use this incense instead.
Su Peisheng.
Yes.
Station capable servants in the
Palace of Eternal Longevity.
Your Majesty, rest assured.
I've made proper arrangements.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Grace to Your Highness Consort Lumière.
All rise.
Yes.
Your Majesty, Concubine Vertu was afraid
that other servants could not
properly serve Consort Lumière upon her return.
Therefore, she sent Xiao-Yunzi back
to serve Consort Lumière.
When it comes to caring for Consort Lumière,
no one comes close to Concubine Vertu.
Now, I'm going to pay my respects to Imperial Mother.
I will come see you tonight.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
His Majesty departs.
Peace to Your Highness Consort Lumière!
Rise.
Yes.
How is everything with Concubine Vertu?
Good, everything is good.
It's just that it has been a while since
His Majesty visited the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Concubine Vertu and we servants have been
looking forward to Your Highness's return.
There aren't many familiar faces in the palace anymore.
The Household Department assigned a few new maids
including Petunia and Clover to serve Your Highness.
Has there been any unrest
regarding my return to the palace?
Your Highness needn't pay any heed to
what those people are saying.
Although,
I heard the officials argued endlessly over the grand
refurbishment of the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
Even State Prince Heng strongly opposed it.
They all wrote to His Majesty to say...
They say: it's already unheard of that a banished
concubine could return to the palace,
let alone being so lavished upon;
and that I am an "ominous flood" that will
bring misfortune to the harem, don't they?
It's not as unpleasant as that.
Your Highness is the mother of the Fourth Prince,
who prayed for blessings upon our nation.
Who would dare spread rumors of banishment?
The court officials are sour about things.
It doesn't matter.
Your Highness doesn't need to pay attention.
What matters is the Palace of Great Benevolence.
Even if the Palace of Eternal Longevity needed extensive repairs,
it didn't need to be this lavish.
Didn't you hear that "the Empress
made thoughtful contributions"?
I was wondering why she would be so kind-hearted.
It seems that with one hand she was
pleasing His Majesty to earn herself a good name;
But with the other hand,
it makes outsiders think that I am a
"minx bewitching her master,"
confirming their belief that I am "an ominous flood".
Leave the past in the past.
It's more important to think forward.
Jinxi.
Bring Wen Shichu here.
Your Highness, please rest assured.
The incense does not contain ingredients
like musk that would harm the baby.
The pear scent is light and sweet.
It is ideal for calming the nerves.
I can never be too careful.
Your Highness is right to be careful.
But I need to mention one more thing:
Ylang-ylang flowers should never be
in the same room with this scent.
Ylang-ylang is a non-toxic herb
and it can calm the mind.
Is it because the two have antagonistic properties?
No, they do not.
It's just that, when they combine,
they can stimulate sensual desires.
The palace forbids concubines to
seduce His Majesty with stimulating herbs.
Who would dare use this?
What's more, ylang-ylang is rare.
Your Highness, the Fourth Prince
requests an audience.
You may leave now.
I bid Your Highness goodbye.
Show the Fourth Prince in.
Yes.
Peace to Mother.
Rise, quickly.
Let me have a look at you.
You've grown up. How tall you are now!
It's been a long time, Mother.
I missed you a lot.
Her Highness Concubine Vertu told me
as long as Mother is here,
I am no longer an unwanted child.
With you, Hongli,
I'm also not alone anymore.
I know that Mother cares about me
more than anyone in the palace.
Hongli, you know that I care about you.
Let me tell you a few things.
You have many mothers in the palace.
And you have Imperial Mother and Imperial Father.
But you have to remember,
No matter who your mother was at birth
and no matter how much you miss her,
in the open and behind closed doors,
I am now your birth mother.
You can't think less of yourself.
Because you are a son of the Aisin Gioro and Niohuru families.
My dignity and disgrace are entwined with yours.
Yes, Mother, I understand.
There is no lack of hearsay
about my return to the palace.
Simply turn a deaf ear to it.
You only need to remember that
you are His Majesty's son -
an honorable prince,
just the same as other princes.
Yes.
I will remember all you've said.
Good.
I bow before Your Majesty.
Grandest wishes to Your Majesty
for good health and a millennium of peace.
Rise and have a seat.
I thank Your Majesty.
Autumn, serve the tea.
Yes.
Today is not special, neither the full nor new moon,
yet Consort Lumière arrived before anyone else.
I should have paid my respects
immediately after my return yesterday.
Therefore, I am here to beg for Your Majesty's forgiveness.
You are with child and have just returned
from the Temple of Pure Dew.
You should take your time and rest.
We will see each other from day to day.
No need to rush to pay your respects.
Your Majesty is generous and caring.
But I dare not be impertinent.
While I was away, I dared not forget
Your Majesty's benevolent graces,
for which I prayed every day.
I had these prayer beads consecrated,
hoping to be able to present them
to Your Majesty one day.
I wish Your Majesty peace and good health year over year.
Consort Lumière is very thoughtful.
This gift is secondary
to the fact that you have a wise mind,
and knew you would eventually meet me again one day.
Your Majesty, please put on a blossom.
Just as before, Consort Lumière follows this etiquette
without the slightest mistake.
It's my duty to serve Your Majesty.
I dare not forget the proper protocols.
Several years have passed in a blink
but time has left not a trace on your countenance.
In fact, your charm has only grown.
It's true that the fleeting seasons
tenderly favor Consort Lumière.
Unlike me, growing old, like pearls turning yellow.
Your Majesty is the "mother of the nation,"
like the mudan peony, poised
and magnificently beautiful.
Why does Your Majesty speak such sad words?
All flowers blossom and fade.
A peony is no different.
It is only a matter of time.
Your Majesty, the concubines are here
to pay their respects.
They are waiting outside.
Consort Lumière, let's go together.
Now that Consort Lumière is back,
Consort Estime, you should take
Princess Longyue to visit Consort Lumière often.
After all, Consort Lumière is Longyue's birth mother.
After Consort Lumière gives birth,
Princess Longyue should be sent back to
the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
A foster mother, no matter how close to her,
cannot compare to her birth mother.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Sit, please.
Where is Noble Lady Paix?
Why did not she come today?
Your Majesty, Lady Paix
said she was not feeling well this morning.
Therefore, she is unable to
pay her respects to Your Majesty.
Since she’s unwell,
her doctors will continue her care.
Consort Lumière, since you’re pregnant,
you must carefully nourish yourself.
Get more rest and avoid moving around excessively.
You are excused from unnecessary courtesies.
I thank Your Majesty.
Having both the Fourth Prince and the Princess,
Consort Lumière is blessed by Heaven
in a way not everyone could be.
All right. Let's call it a day.
You all may leave now.
We bid Your Majesty goodbye.
If Your Highness likes the flowers of the "coupling joy" tree,
we can pick some and put them into sachets.
They can be kept for a while, but not eternally.
Even if we make them into sachets,
they will wither away eventually.
Leave them be.
Peace to Consort Lumière.
I’ve never seen you before.
Your Highness, I am the Noble Lady surnamed Ye.
I've been sick recently,
so I was unable to meet Your Highness.
Then how do you know that I am Consort Lumière?
Your Highness returned to the palace
with a grand procession.
Who wouldn’t know Your Highness?
Since you are not feeling well,
why haven’t you stayed in your palace to rest?
You will feel worse once the sun gets hotter.
I thank Your Highness for your caring words.
Why did you collect so many petals?
The imperial doctors said, to treat my illness,
silk tree flowers should be added to my medicine.
That’s why I’m collecting them.
Otherwise, the fallen petals would only
be left to decay into the soil.
That would be a pity.
I feel humbled by your tender feeling for
"the fragrant and fair."
Your Highness,
my illness restrains me from conversing with Your Highness.
I take my leave.
How can she be so impertinent!
She’s just abusing His Majesty's favor of her.
It’s no wonder they say she’s solitary and unruly.
Your Highness.
To soothe prenatal qi, I asked our kitchen to prepare
this sangjisheng soup, stewed with duzhong and beimu.
Please have a taste.
It tastes good.
To calm the prenatal body and mind,
this is much better than those bitter and nauseating tonics.
My Lady, Her Highness Concubine Vertu is here.
Show her in, quickly!
I heard all that at the door.
Now that you're pregnant,
you’re getting more difficult to please.
I was just thinking about you,
and here you are!
Go bring Meizhuang’s favorite red date hawthorn cakes.
And serve Biluochun for tea. Hurry!
You remember I like red date hawthorn cake.
And I was mindful that you dislike
greasy foods when you're pregnant.
So I made this refreshing
osmanthus lotus root cake for you.
Have some.
No matter how many years have passed,
your lotus root cake is still the tastiest.
I often thought of it while I was away.
I'll make it for you every day if you like.
Huan’er, I could not have imagined that
we would again have days when we could sit and talk.
Now that I have returned, you should be happy.
Of course I’m happy about this.
However,
once again your days will be as restless as before.
I’m not sure whether such a life
is good for you, or bad.
Perhaps ...
I shouldn’t have told you the news about your father.
If you hadn't informed me,
I would be sitting around idly while my father
was dying from his sickness in Ningguta.
I understand.
You and I and many others ...
we live not for ourselves.
Our parents and siblings, and the good names of our clans -
they all burden our hearts.
Whatever the reasons, I'm happy that we're back together.
Fortunately, my father has returned to
the capital to receive treatment.
I can finally breathe a sigh of relief.
The Empress will have worse migraine attacks now.
But she was no fool.
She easily delayed your return with the
"Roof mansion impinging on the Moon" ploy.
You must be careful.
I know.
With that being said,
we'd better have our own people
in the Astrological Office.
The Deputy Astrological Official Ji Weisheng
is very dedicated to his duties.
He would be a competent candidate.
The Head Official speaks but his
"words come from another mouth."
Perhaps he needs a break.
That shouldn't be difficult.
“People eat the five grains and sickness can follow."
My Lady, the head of Household Department,
Liang Duorui has brought some newly made fabrics.
Show him in.
Yes.
Sir, please come in.
Peace to Your Highnesses
Consort Lumière and Concubine Vertu.
Rise.
His Majesty said Your Highness will have the first pick
of the new offerings of Sichuan and Suzhou brocade.
Xiao-Yunzi, come here.
Send the pale green brocade to Lady Paix.
She seems to like green and the color suits her.
I bid Your Highness goodbye.
You've met Lady Paix?
Yes, I have. She's truly different.
My Lady, did you forget how she was?
Why give her such fine brocade?
I was just thinking about
who the color would look good on.
I asked Xiao-Yunzi to take it to her
because this color suits her.
Why do you treat her like a foe
when you've only met her once?
I just can't tolerate her crass attitude.
Who does she think she is?
That's enough talking.
It's just a piece of brocade.
Xiao-Yunzi, tell Lady Paix that it's hot today
so she need not thank me in person.
Yes.
But I have to tell you
there's no need to be too nice to her.
The Empress Dowager disliked her from the start.
She's arrogant and aloof.
No one in the harem gets along with her.
However, His Majesty is fond of her,
so some courtesies must be extended.
Mother, where are we going?
Longyue, I'm taking you to pay respects to Consort Lumière.
Was she the one wearing the pretty dress that day?
You're very smart. Yes, that's her.
Is she also my mother?
Why haven‘t I seen her before?
Longyue, because Consort Lumière
was not living in the palace.
Longyue, you will visit
Consort Lumière more often from now.
Consort Lumière adores you.
Consort Lumière is pretty. I like her, too.
But - But I like you the most, Mother.
You're even better at embroidery now.
My child can certainly rely on this aunt.
You'd better make some more bibs!
Haven't I made enough for Longyue?
Consort Estime and I made nearly all her clothes ourselves.
If you keep having children the rest of your life,
will I be making clothes for you the rest of my days?
What a smart way to "add beads to your abacus!"
Your Highness, Consort Estime is here
with Princess Longyue.
Show them in now!
Aiya, it's so nice and cool here.
After three months of refurbishment
at His Majesty's behest,
this palace is as marvelous as expected.
Longyue, greet Her Highness.
What do you say?
Peace to Consort Lumière.
It wouldn't have been proper to thank you
in front of the crowd yesterday.
Seeing you today, Estime,
I extend my gratitude for your taking attentive care
of Longyue and treating her as your own daughter.
Lumière, we are at the same rank.
You must not bow like this. Please rise.
If I hadn't had Longyue by my side,
bringing me laughter and joy,
I don't know how I would've gotten through these years.
In the past, Lady Cao and
Consort Astuce both had children,
and later Consort Honnête had
Princess Wenyi "running around her knees."
How I envied them.
Mother, wipe wipe. Longyue will be good.
Silly girl, what "Mother"?
Consort Lumière is your real mother.
Go, let her hold you.
Good girl, let Mother kiss you.
Can I give you a hug?
Let mother hold you.
Mother, you don't want me anymore!
Longyue, be good.
How could Mother not want you?
All right. It's all right.
Yue'er, good girl, come here.
Will you come to me?
Come.
Yue'er, my dear, let me explain.
It's not that Consort Estime doesn't want you,
but now one more person will also love you.
Isn't that good?
See? Consort Lumière adores you so much, doesn't she?
I adore Longyue too.
Longyue, would you give Mother a kiss?
You're not my mother.
Lumière, Yue'er is still very young.
You just came back to the palace,
and she's not familiar with you.
Your Highness, Her Majesty the Empress
will soon get up from her nap.
Understood. Is the sedan chair ready?
Yes, I've asked the sedan to wait outside
the Palace of Eternal Longevity.
Why not pay respects to the Empress Dowager with me,
since you just returned yesterday?
Yes.
Yes. It's good that you can accompany each other.
Then... I'll head back now.
Mother, don't go!
Yue'er, be good.
You're going to live in the
Palace of Eternal Longevity from now on.
You'll spend time with your birth mother now, won't you?
No! No!
Consort Lumière came back and now
Mother doesn't want me anymore.
Why did Consort Lumière come back?
Longyue, how can you say that?
Lumière,
I've never taught her to say such things.
It's because His Majesty never allowed me
to speak of you in front of Longyue...
I was banished.
It's reasonable that His Majesty didn't
tell the princess about me.
Longyue is just a child.
Please don't be upset.
Although His Majesty concealed it,
his heart always held a place for you.
Longyue, look at you.
You've upset your birth mother.
Now, apologize to your birth mother.
Go.
Consort Lumière, please don't be mad.
I am ... apologizing to you, Consort Lumière.
Would you please not be mad?
Don't cry. Don't cry.
I caused this
by asking her to call me Mother so abruptly.
Who would have expected that we'd never meet again
only three days after she was born?
In her heart, Estime,
she regards you as her Mother.
Seeing how she calls you Mother,
I cannot adequately express my gratitude.
Lumière, please don't talk as if we were strangers.
Don’t cry.
Now that I'm pregnant,
I won't be able to look after Longyue.
I hope you can take care of Longyue
before I give birth.
Would you, Estime, make the effort for me?
Since you have so much trust in me, I surely will.
Not just several months,
I would happily look after her my whole life.
Lumière, don't worry, and nourish yourself well.
Huan'er is right,
she is pregnant
and the doctors said her condition is unstable.
She should be careful not to fall or be bumped into.
Longyue is still very young.
We wouldn't want any accident to happen.
That's right. In that case,
I will take Longyue back to
the Palace of Universal Happiness for now.
It’s getting late.
You’d better go pay respects to Her Majesty.
We shall ...
take our leave.
Let’s go.
Your Majesty has already started taking your medicine?
I should serve Your Majesty the medicine.
You came just in time.
Apart from Bamboo,
I feel the most comfortable with your attendance.
I bow in respect before Your Majesty.
May eternal grace and good health be with Your Majesty.
You have returned.
How do you like living in the Palace of Eternal Longevity?
Your Majesty, the luxuriousness of the Palace
of Eternal Longevity unsettles me greatly.
It is luxurious indeed, but appropriate
since the emperor dotes on you.
This medicine leaves a bitter taste in my mouth.
Might as well pour it out.
I've been saying Your Majesty
is getting younger by the day!
And Your Majesty doesn't believe me.
Now Your Majesty refuses to take
medicine because it's bitter
just like a child!
Truly Your Majesty is growing younger.
I've always seen you as stable and prudent.
Now you've learned to "talk with an oiled tongue."
Since the medicine is bitter, I just hope
to coax a smile from Your Majesty.
Here.
A pregnant woman shouldn't be kneeling for so long.
You'll help me rinse my mouth.
Yes, Your Majesty.
You are more skillful in your service now.
No wonder the emperor still clung to thoughts of you
even long after you left for the Temple of Pure Dew.
You really have become
"a bewitching minx to her master."
Your Majesty's words inspire terror in me.
Terror?
Consort Lumière, you are the bearer of
an imperial heir and the emperor's deep favor.
Why would you feel terrified?
Because I am the bearer of an offense.
When His Majesty cherished his
past affections and visited me at the temple,
I felt eternally grateful.
I didn't expect to become pregnant from the visit.
His Majesty has shown exceptional pity for me
only because of his care for the heir
and the imperial bloodline.
Are you saying
your reunion with the emperor
was merely a chance encounter
rather than a plotted effort to regain his favor?
I dare not deceive Your Majesty.
It was not a chance encounter.
I had been unwell because I left the
palace during the first postnatal month.
So, I moved to the living quarters at Peak Lingyun.
When His Majesty visited and
didn't see me at the temple,
he thought I was still ill.
So His Majesty went to Peak Lingyun to see me.
Is that so?
I've blamed you wrongly, it seems.
It is my fault that I did not make a
timely report of the matter to Your Majesty.
I admit my offense.
When you insisted on leaving the palace,
you were even able to leave behind
your newborn daughter.
Why, now, are you are willing to
reconcile with the emperor
and have a child with him?
Your Majesty ...
I am talking to her, not you.
His Majesty is the sovereign of the nation,
and not just my husband.
Even though I was saddened by
what happened in court to my father,
I despised those who defamed him, but I never dared to hold a grudge against His Majesty.
I insisted on leaving the palace
because I thought His Majesty had lost all
affection for me, turning my hopes to ashes.
But when His Majesty came to visit me,
I knew he was not without affection.
It's an unimagined fortune that I could return to the palace.
Now I only want to devote myself to
serving His Majesty to mend my mistakes.
You may rise.
I thank Your Majesty.
You're usually the considerate one.
Why didn't you remind me to ask
Consort Lumière to rise?
I may be sick and confused, but are you too?
Your Majesty, Consort Lumière was kneeling
so your grandchild could kneel and bow to you.
How could I stop them from
greeting Your Majesty as a family?
That is very sweet of you.
Grant Consort Lumière a seat.
Don't blame me for being tough on you.
The emperor is my son
so I was afraid he would have another minx by his side.
Now that you are ranked at Consort,
your ensemble is too simple for your title.
I have been practicing Buddhism,
so I don't prefer extravagance.
You are very sensible.
And worthy of the care I've provided these past years.
I was blessed to have Your Majesty's care
bestowed upon me at the Temple of Pure Dew.
I am eternally grateful.
Henceforth, consider the Temple of Pure Dew
as if it never happened.
I will order others to think the same.
You must remember that
your life won't be easy if associated with the Temple of Pure Dew.
You are four months pregnant, correct?
Yes.
The Emperor is getting on in years,
and his favored concubines
do not bring peace to the harem.
Now that you are back,
you should always advise restraint to him.
He will listen to you, more or less.
I will obey Your Majesty's guidance.
I will fulfill the duties and virtues of a Consort.
You are astute. I need not belabor my point.
Since you spoke of the duties of a Consort，
you must respect the Empress.
The Empress treats me very kindly.
I am very grateful towards Her Majesty.
Good.
You and Consort Lumière are like sisters.
She already bears a second child.
Won't you put in more effort?
I've always thought highly of you.
But you do not expend enough effort on the Emperor.
Currently there is no one to properly advise His Majesty ....
I constantly worry about this.
I understand, Your Majesty.
Understanding is not enough.
You must take action.
If you two can serve and assist the Emperor,
then I can put my mind at ease.
Longyue is so estranged from me.
It breaks my heart.
Don't blame either Consort Estime or Longyue.
It was His Majesty who didn't allow Longyue to know.
Two years ago, a maid accidentally let slip
that Longyue's birth mother was at the
Temple of Pure Dew.
His Majesty was infuriated and had her flogged to death.
Longyue is very attached to Consort Estime.
It's clear that Consort Estime has treated her very well.
When I saw how close they are,
I knew that even if I took Longyue back,
it would only drive her further away from me.
And would also hurt my relations with Consort Estime.
I'm glad you can see that.
Longyue is still young.
If you are good to her, she will warm up to you naturally.
After all, she is your child.
Lower the sedan!
Quick! Lower the sedan!
We are at fault, Your Highness.
Huan'er, are you all right?
You idiots!
How could you be so careless when
Her Highness is sitting on the sedan!
You'll have your heads off
if I report this to the Household Department!
Your Highness, please forgive us!
Don't you know how to walk properly?
How could you slip on this road?
This - This stone pavement is usually easy to walk on.
But today there are some pebbles
strewn on the ground,
which ... caused us to slip.
Your Highness.
You think I'm a fool?
Is this the shortest path back
to Her Highness's palace?
Why did you take this road?
We dare not fool you, miss.
Although this is not the shortest path,
it is the coolest path in summer.
Thankfully, Her Highness is not hurt.
If anything happened to Her Highness,
our heads would not be enough to
compensate for our offense.
Where are we right now?
Concubine Délice's Palace of Gathering Excellence
is just steps ahead.
Usually, if there are no special orders,
the porters would go back on the same route.
Since it is quite hot today, of course they chose this path.
It seems that someone had their heart set on them stumbling.
This is only the second day since my return
and somebody is already feeling impatient.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.